<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title></title>
		<description></description>
		<link></link>
		<language>en-us</language>
    <pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2013 01:38:28 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2013 01:38:28 -0400</lastBuildDate>
		<atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
	<item>
		<title>Neutron Stars and Other End-Points</title>
		<description>&lt;h1 id='formation_of_neutron_stars'&gt;Formation of Neutron Stars&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Iron core held up by Electron Degeneracy Pressure&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Neutralization causes iron core to become mostly neutrons, held up by NDP&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Since neutrons are heavier than electrons, the density required for that pressure is much greater, so the neutron star is much denser&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Most pressure holding up a neutron star is NDP &amp;amp; strong nuclear force&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Balance between gravitation force &amp;amp; NDP/strong force&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id='what_happens_at_greater_densities'&gt;What Happens at greater Densities?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neutron stars can be in a binary system&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Mass transfer can increase angular velocity &amp;amp; mass of n-star&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;As you add more mass to n-star, it grows smaller and there is a Chandrasekhar-like limit for n-stars&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;As gravity overcomes NDP, there is no new equilibrium for the falling star&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;All material falls towards being a single point&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Forms a hugely dense core.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Event horizon: boundary between when you can access the outside universe and when you can no longer communicate with the outside world.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Why? Escape Velocity. The escape speed is &amp;gt; than speed of light&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;V_esc = sqrt( 2&lt;em&gt;G&lt;/em&gt;M / R ) or V_esc ~= sqrt ( 2&lt;em&gt;M / R)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Earth&amp;#8217;s escape speed is 11 km/s&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Black holes can also be formed by sufficiently heavy stars collapsing&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;If the mass of the star is above or around 25 solar masses, the iron core collapses and doesn&amp;#8217;t find a stable point when NDP sets in.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id='special_relativity'&gt;Special Relativity&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Merger of Newtonian treatment of motion with electromagnetism&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Uses absolute motion of light (light always moves at the same velocity) instead of absolute time&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;The laws of physics are the same in every inertial frame&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;An inertial frame is any non-accelerated frame of reference&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;An object at motion from one frame is at rest from the opposite frame&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Motion is relative to the frame of reference&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;The speed of light is the same in every inertial frame&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2013 12:32:00 -0500</pubDate>
		<link>/notes/astr102/Neutron-Stars-and-Other-end-points.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">/notes/astr102/Neutron-Stars-and-Other-end-points.html</guid>
	</item>

	<item>
		<title>Transport Layer - Multiplexing Error Detection and UDP</title>
		<description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Executes only on the end systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transport vs. Network:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transport layer is data transfer between processes&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Network layer is data transfer between machines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TCP: reliable, in-order, unicast&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UDP: unreliable, unordered (&amp;#8216;best-effort&amp;#8217;), unicast &amp;amp; multicast - Provides minimal error detection&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unicast: 1 to 1 connection&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multicast: 1 to many connection, selected segment of multiple recipients - Live streaming audio, video, similar to broadcast delivery&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anycast: 1 to many connection, doesn&amp;#8217;t matter if all of them get it, but any one of the them should it - Service that is provided identically on many different servers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id='services_not_provided'&gt;Services not provided&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Performance&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;non-unicast delivery models&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id='multiplexing'&gt;Multiplexing&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each end-system has a single protocol &amp;#8216;stack&amp;#8217; - Stack is shared between all applications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multiplexing allows multiple applications to use network simultaneously&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;De-multiplexing delivers received data to appropriate application&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on IP addresses and sender and receiver port #s - Source and destination port # carried in each segment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;De-multiplexing is helped by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IP address identifies the receiving machine&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Port # identifies the receiving process&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;De-multiplexing action depends on connection or connection-less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UDP de-multiplexes segments to the socket&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uses a 2-tuple: ( destIP, destPort# )&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Socket is &amp;#8216;owned&amp;#8217; by some process allocated by the OS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TCP de-multiplexes segments to a connection&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id='udp_delivery'&gt;UDP Delivery&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;best-effort delivery&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Goal: provide error detection &amp;amp; multiplexing but no delivery guarantees&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Characteristics of network layer determine reliability of data delivery&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&amp;#8216;Bare bones&amp;#8217; transport protocol&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Segments may be lost, delivered out of order or multiple times&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;No handshake between UDP sender and receiver&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Each UDP segment is handled independently of others&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id='why_udp'&gt;Why UDP?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Often used for streaming multimedia applications&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Loss-tolerant applications&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Rate-sensitive applications&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Periodic or redundant data&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;DNS: small messages doesn&amp;#8217;t need heavy-duty setup&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;SNMP: used by systems administrators to manage the network&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Routing protocols: exchange information about link state of nodes in network&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id='checksum_computation'&gt;Checksum computation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UDP checksum allows receiver to detect errors in transmitted segment&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Errors are &amp;#8216;flipped&amp;#8217; bits&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Sender treats contents as a sequence of 16 bit ints&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Sum the segment&amp;#8217;s contents and place the 1&amp;#8217;s complement of the sum into checksum field.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id='reliability'&gt;Reliability&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Goal: provide a reliable underlying channel&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Characteristics of underlying channel determines complexity of reliable communications&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Issues: State is required at sender &amp;amp; receiver and number of control messages exchanged&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2013 11:02:00 -0500</pubDate>
		<link>/notes/comp431/Multiplexing-Error-Dectection-and-UDP.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">/notes/comp431/Multiplexing-Error-Dectection-and-UDP.html</guid>
	</item>

	<item>
		<title>Multiplexing, Error Dectection, & UDP</title>
		<description></description>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2013 11:02:00 -0500</pubDate>
		<link>/notes/comp431/Multiplexing%2C-Error-Dectection%2C-%26-UDP.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">/notes/comp431/Multiplexing%2C-Error-Dectection%2C-%26-UDP.html</guid>
	</item>

	<item>
		<title>Solar Composition After the Main Sequence</title>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;After a while, large stars start fusing carbon, oxygen, neon, magnesium, and silicon. The only true ash component is iron (i.e., iron-group elements). Iron is the turning point of the fusion/ fission. Fusion reactions above Iron-group require energy to fuse rather than release energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The brightness of a galaxy is comparable to the brightness of a supernova.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id='novae_or_classical_novae'&gt;Novae or Classical Novae&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Related to white dwarf stars. Can give a white dwarf a second chance. Once its companion stars fills its Roche lobe, it begins to transfer mass. The increase of hydrogen causes instant fusion to occur on the surface, throwing off a portion of the star&amp;#8217;s surface. At this point, the star explodes in a nova, where the luminosity increases by a factor of 10,000 over the course of a few days and lasts for about a month. Some novae only happen once, but others recur periodically after the companion star refills its Roche lobe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id='type_ii_supernovae'&gt;Type II Supernovae&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will produce a type II supernova. The core of the massive star begins to be composed mostly of iron. There comes a point where the size of the iron core is greater than a solar mass itself. When the density is ~ 1E9 times water and the temperature is about 1E9 K, the process reverses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The high temperature allows gamma rays to &amp;#8216;smash&amp;#8217; or split up iron particles into 14 He. If the temperature is even hotter, the gamma ray can split He into 2 neutrons and 2 protons. In a matter of a second, the iron gets busted up into Helium and into neutrons and protons. This is an exothermic reaction, so where is the energy coming from? Gravitation potential energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the core shrinks in size, the gravitation energy becomes heat which increases the speed of the reaction. This shrinking causes a chain reaction where the core keeps shrinking and smashing more iron. Electrons and protons interact to form a neutron and an electron neutrino. Since electrons provide the pressure for the star, the star shrinks in size as its electrons are depleted. The star continues to collapse until it shrinks to a radius of ~10 km. This means the density goes from 1E9 to 1E15 the density of water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The density of the core creates an neutron degeneracy liquid (since they are fermions and cannot occupy the same quantum state. See Pauli Exclusion Principle). The pressure of the neutron degeneracy pressure causes the core to &amp;#8216;bounce back&amp;#8217; to a slightly larger. This creates a shock-wave that pushes the gas falling into the core out. The shock-wave goes through the entire material of the collapsing star and ejects it to interstellar space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id='type_i_supernovae'&gt;Type I Supernovae&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Completely different reaction, but puts out about the same energy as a type II supernova. A type I supernova is associated with a white dwarf in a binary star system. Helium gets added to the carbon-oxygen core of the white dwarf. This process lasts for a long time, but eventually it can greatly increase the mass of the white dwarf. This only happens if the mass-transfer is slow enough that the hydrogen/ helium doesn&amp;#8217;t immediately ignite b/c of the speed of the transfer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more mass the star has, the more gravity the core has and the more energy is applied to compress the core. Electron degenerate liquid is mostly incompressible, but you can compress it with enough force. The more mass you add to the white dwarf. Because of the nature of the gas, as you add mass the star&amp;#8217;s radius decreases (counter intuitive, yes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At ~1.4 solar masses, the is a cutoff point called the Chrandrasekhar mass. At 1.4 solar masses, the radius is so small that it is almost 0. At this point, the carbon and oxygen are compressed enough that they can start fusing. Very quickly after that, the magnesium produce burns, and so on until iron-group elements. All this happens in about a second or so. This causes a giant explosion of energy. It starts in the core (where it&amp;#8217;s densest), and creates a burning front, which burns through the rest of the fuel left in the star and leaves a bunch of iron ash. This is equivalent to a bunch of H-bombs going off at once.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2013 12:30:00 -0500</pubDate>
		<link>/notes/astr102/Solar-Composition-After-the-Main-Sequence.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">/notes/astr102/Solar-Composition-After-the-Main-Sequence.html</guid>
	</item>

	<item>
		<title>HTTP Protocol</title>
		<description>&lt;h1 id='caching'&gt;Caching&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Conditional GET&lt;/dt&gt;

&lt;dd&gt;If the object in the browser cache is &amp;#8216;fresh&amp;#8217;, the server won&amp;#8217;t resent the response. Conditional GET has last modified date from cache. Browsers save object in cache with a last modified tag. Server can respond with a 304 Not Modified message if the image hasn&amp;#8217;t changed since that date. If modified, it returns a 200 OK with the object&amp;#8217;s data.&lt;/dd&gt;

&lt;dt&gt;What is the average time to retrieve a web object?&lt;/dt&gt;

&lt;dd&gt;T_mean = hit_ratio * t_cache + (1 - hit_ratio) * t_server&lt;/dd&gt;

&lt;dt&gt;What is the mean access time from a disk cache?&lt;/dt&gt;

&lt;dd&gt;Depends on many different things, but in the area of 1-10 ms&lt;/dd&gt;

&lt;dt&gt;So, if the hit ratio is 60%?&lt;/dt&gt;

&lt;dd&gt;T_mean = .6 * 10 ms + .4 * 1000 ms = 406 ms&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a disk cache reduced the average response time from 1 second to ~400 ms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;What determines the hit ratio?&lt;/dt&gt;

&lt;dd&gt;Cache size - can retain more stuff&lt;/dd&gt;

&lt;dd&gt;&lt;em&gt;Locality of references&lt;/em&gt; - how often the same web object requested&lt;/dd&gt;

&lt;dd&gt;How long objects remain &amp;#8216;fresh&amp;#8217; or unchanged&lt;/dd&gt;

&lt;dd&gt;Object references that can&amp;#8217;t be cached. I.E., dynamically generated content, protected content, content purchased each use, content that must be always up-to-date, advertisements (&amp;#8216;pay-per-click&amp;#8217;).&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;h1 id='chapter_2__problem_1'&gt;Chapter 2 - Problem 1&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: dog.com - 20,000 bits - 2&lt;em&gt;50 ms + .2 ms = 100.2 ms&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: dog.com/dog-banner.jpg - 2&lt;em&gt;50 ms + 15 000 / 100 000 000 = 100.15 ms B: cat.com/meow-add.jpg - 2&lt;/em&gt;10 ms + 10 000 / 100 000 000 = 20.1 ms C: bird.com/chirp-add.jpg - 2&lt;em&gt;20 ms + 10 000 / 100 000 000 = 40.1 ms D: cat.com/puss-chow-add.jpg - 2&lt;/em&gt;10 ms + 10 000 / 100 000 000 = 20.1 ms&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;B: www.dog.com/dog-chow-add.jpg - 2&lt;em&gt;50 ms + 0.1 ms = 100.1 ms D: www2.dog.com/cookie.crumb - 2&lt;/em&gt;50 ms + 0.05 ms = 100.05 ms&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Persistent, reusing domain first&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: dog.com - 2&lt;em&gt;50 ms + .2 ms = 100.2 ms A: dog.com/dog-banner.jpg - 50 ms + .15 ms = 50.15 ms A: dog.com/dog-chow-add.jpg - 50 ms + .1 ms = 50.1 ms&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;B: cat.com/meow-add.jpg - 2&lt;em&gt;10 ms + .1 ms = 20.1 ms B: cat.com/puss-chow-add.jpg - 10 ms + .1 ms = 10.1 ms&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2013 11:07:00 -0500</pubDate>
		<link>/notes/comp431/HTTP-Protocol.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">/notes/comp431/HTTP-Protocol.html</guid>
	</item>

	<item>
		<title>Red Giants and Planetary Nebulae</title>
		<description>&lt;h1 id='white_dwarf'&gt;White Dwarf&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M ~= 0.6 solar masses&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;R ~= 0.01 solar radii&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Composed of electron degenerate matter. How common are they? If the star&amp;#8217;s initial mass is less than 8 solar masses, the star will always become a white dwarf. If it&amp;#8217;s heavier than that, it would form a neutron star or, with a supernova, a black hole. Therefore, white dwarfs are relatively common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example: Sirius B&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id='globular_star_clusters'&gt;Globular Star Clusters&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most common place to find them is a globular star cluster. A globular star cluster is bound by gravity into a rough sphere. The turn-off point of the main sequence helps tell how long ago a star cluster formed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id='binary_star_systems'&gt;Binary Star Systems&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two Roche Lobes around each star. Somewhat teardrop-shaped. Somewhat like a figure-eight shape when viewed together. Roche lobes determine places where a free-floating object would be bound to that object. As long as the Roche Lobes are greater than the surface of the star, then the gases of the star are bound to the star. Once the star swells in size, it can exceed its Roche Lobe. It then takes on the shape of the Roche Lobe. Once it exceeds the Roche Lobe, you have mass spill over via the Lagrange Point into the Roche Lobe of the companion star. This mass-transfer can result in the lighter star becoming the heavier star in the system. This mass increase accelerates the star&amp;#8217;s aging. This results in both stars being giants at once. Thus, the two stars can fill there Roche Lobes and merge into one single envelope.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2013 12:30:00 -0500</pubDate>
		<link>/notes/astr102/Red-Giants-and-Planetary-Nebulae.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">/notes/astr102/Red-Giants-and-Planetary-Nebulae.html</guid>
	</item>

	<item>
		<title>Stellar Evolution</title>
		<description>&lt;h2 id='spectroscopic_inspection_of_nebulae'&gt;Spectroscopic Inspection of Nebulae&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forbidden Lines, OIII spectrum lines. They are called forbidden b/c they can&amp;#8217;t replicate in a lab. It is caused by oxygen being ionized twice (losing two valence electrons). We can&amp;#8217;t observe doubly ionize oxygen in a lab b/c the density of the oxygen in the best vacuum chamber in a lab that the oxygen will collide with another oxygen atom before it can drop an energy level and emit a photon. The gas in OIII emission nebulae is so rarefied that it can spontaneous drop down to a lower level from the OIII state. OIII emissions aren&amp;#8217;t generally visible (i.e., observable only in spectroscopy), but when it is it glows green.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='protostellar_evolution'&gt;Proto-stellar Evolution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the mass of a proto-stellar object is below .08 solar masses then it isn&amp;#8217;t dense enough to start burning hydrogen in fusion. Very low mass objects such as Jupiter (1/1000 solar mass) generally don&amp;#8217;t burn, but there are objects such as brown dwarfs. Brown dwarfs don&amp;#8217;t burn hydrogen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='brown_dwarfs'&gt;Brown Dwarfs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally they start at a certain temperature and gradually cool (i.e., over 10 billion years).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='red_giants'&gt;Red Giants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gradually the star goes from burning hydrogen at the core and start burning the shell. The core is a non-burning dense helium &amp;#8216;ash.&amp;#8217; Once shell burning starts, it swells 5-10 times larger than it used to be b/c it is putting out more luminosity over time. Because L ~= R^2 * T^4, as the radius increases the surface temperature reduces. The core temperature increases several times due to the shell burning occurring. After the sub-giant branch, it goes from 3 solar radii to 100 solar radii.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the core temperature reaches to 100E6 K, the Helium Flash occurs, and the helium begins to fuse. Hydrogen burning still occurs in the shell. This reaction is referred to as the triple-&amp;#945; reaction. The helium burning does not burn steadily as hydrogen does b/c by the time the helium starts the burn, the density at the center of the star is ~ 10,000 times the density of water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a certain threshold of pressure that the gas/ plasma in the star phase-shifts to a liquid because of the Pauli Exclusion Principle. This phase is called a degenerate electron liquid. This gas is interested because the electrons have pressure b/c they called become closer. This pressure is called Electron Degeneracy Pressure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Red giants develop an onion-skin arrangement of elements in the star, with the heavier elements towards the center of the core. Helium burning creates an ash ball of carbon. If the temperature of the core isn&amp;#8217;t below 600E6 K, it cannot burn the carbon into oxygen. As all the helium is converted to carbon in the core, the star begins to burn helium in a shell around the core. After this, the core is an ash ball of carbon, and there are two shells: one burning hydrogen and one burning helium. This branch of star evolution is termed the asymptotic giant branch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once it reaches a certain temp, it can burn carbon with helium into oxygen. This can only occur when there is electron degeneracy liquid. This creates a series of explosions inside the star.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='nebulae'&gt;Nebulae&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you go up the asymptotic branch, the explosions become strong enough that the star starts to pulse (in radius) and ejects gas into the interstellar medium. This stage of evolution is termed a nebula or planetary nebula. The term planetary nebula came from the fact that early astronomers could only make out a fuzzy gas cloud at first, similar to what you see when you look at a gas giant such as Neptune. Even though the nebula is a sphere of gas, it often looks like a ring b/c we see through more of the hot, glowing gas at the edges of the object.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nebula tend to have a hotter surface temperature because at a certain point most of the outer gas has shed, and you begin to see the hot inner core.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='white_dwarfs'&gt;White Dwarfs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the core cools down from 100,000+ K to 10,000 K, it is now termed a white dwarf. White dwarfs aren&amp;#8217;t very active in terms of size or temperature, but rather gradually cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='misc'&gt;MISC&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Triple-&amp;#945; reaction&lt;/dt&gt;

&lt;dd&gt;4^He + 4^He + 4^He &amp;#8594; 12^C&lt;/dd&gt;

&lt;dt&gt;Carbon-Helium reaction&lt;/dt&gt;

&lt;dd&gt;C-12 + H-4 &amp;#8594; O-16&lt;/dd&gt;

&lt;dt&gt;Mass rule of thumb&lt;/dt&gt;

&lt;dd&gt;star &amp;gt; 0.08 solar mass &amp;gt; brown dwarf &amp;gt; 0.0012 solar mass &amp;gt; planetary object&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;</description>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2013 12:30:00 -0500</pubDate>
		<link>/notes/astr102/Stellar-Evolution.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">/notes/astr102/Stellar-Evolution.html</guid>
	</item>

	<item>
		<title>FTP Programming</title>
		<description>&lt;h2 id='udp_vs_tcp'&gt;UDP vs. TCP&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UDP only looks at the destination socket. TCP is tied to both end points, UDP is tied only to one end point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='tcp_service'&gt;TCP Service&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TCP does not provide timing or minimum bandwidth guarantees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='urls'&gt;URLs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Domain Name&lt;/dt&gt;

&lt;dd&gt;first part of the url, DNS name of the server and where to find the machine Server Port&lt;/dd&gt;

&lt;dd&gt;(optional) specifies a port to connect to on the server Path Name&lt;/dd&gt;

&lt;dd&gt;How to location the object within the server&amp;#8217;s filesystem&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;h2 id='http'&gt;HTTP&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Implements a client &amp;amp; server model. The protocol is independent of who sends the request or what operating system the client or server is running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HTTP uses TCP sockets. Typically HTTP uses port 80. HTTP is an application-layer protocol. HTTP messages specified by RFC 1945 (HTTP 1.0) &amp;amp; RFC 2616 (HTTP 1.1)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;HTTP 1.0&lt;/dt&gt;

&lt;dd&gt;One request, response interaction per connection HTTP 1.1&lt;/dd&gt;

&lt;dd&gt;Persistent connections - connection doesn&amp;#8217;t close at server response&lt;/dd&gt;

&lt;dd&gt;Pipelined connections - writing to a socket multiple times without waiting for a response each time. Speeds up&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HTTP is &amp;#8216;stateless.&amp;#8217; Server maintains no information about past browser requests. Why? Some servers are distributed&amp;em;they don&amp;#8217;t have the ability to share memory between processes. The process might crash, and if you maintained state the server would have to restore the state. How? Databases? This increases the complexity of the protocol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two types of HTTP message formats: &lt;em&gt;request&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;response&lt;/em&gt; messages, both written in ASCII text format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id='http_example'&gt;HTTP Example&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) User enters URL: www.unc.edu/someDept/home.index&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) Referenced object contains HTML text &amp;amp; references to 10 JPEG images&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) Browser sends HTTP &amp;#8216;GET&amp;#8217; request to server&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4) Server retrieves and sends the file&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5) Browser will read the file and sequentially make 10 separate requests for the embedded JPEG images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See HTTP 1.0 example slide&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id='http_message_protocol'&gt;HTTP Message Protocol&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
method &amp;lt;SP&amp;gt; path &amp;lt;SP&amp;gt; version &amp;lt;CR&amp;gt;&amp;lt;LF&amp;gt; // Request line
header field name &amp;quot;:&amp;quot; value &amp;lt;CR&amp;gt;&amp;lt;LF&amp;gt; //Optional
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
GET /~jasleen HTTP/1.0
Connection: Keep-Alive
User-Agent: Mozilla/4.74 [en] (WinNT; U)
Host: example.com
Accept: x-type/mime-type
Accept-Encoding: gzip
Accept-Language: en
Accept-Charset: iso-8859-1,*,utf-8
Cookie: DOMAIN=8a8b64
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2013 11:20:00 -0500</pubDate>
		<link>/notes/comp431/FTP-Programming.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">/notes/comp431/FTP-Programming.html</guid>
	</item>

	<item>
		<title>Stellar Clouds</title>
		<description>&lt;h1 id='cloud_properties'&gt;Cloud Properties&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gas clouds are very sparse, but very large and stellar distances are great so it can form hundreds of 1000&amp;#8217;s of stars and occlude a lot of light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='how_do_we_see_them'&gt;How do we see them?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gas clouds glow under spectra other than visible light. Why? Transitions occur inside cloud that emit radiation. Spin-flip transition of an electron in neutral hydrogen emits 21 cm photon radiation. Faster vibration to slower vibration also emits photon radiation as does faster to slower rotation of molecules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='how_do_they_stay_togetherseparate'&gt;How do they stay together/separate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the interstellar medium, the gas physics is somewhat different that gas law. Gases can radiate energy into space, lowering its gas pressure. Gas regions can drop out relative to the main cloud. Cloud fragmentation leads to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id='star_formation'&gt;Star Formation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stars form outside the main sequence and gradually settle onto to the main sequence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class='toc'&gt;
&lt;h1 class='toc-header'&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/h1&gt;

* This is a stub for the toc.
{:toc}

&lt;/div&gt;</description>
		<pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2013 12:26:00 -0500</pubDate>
		<link>/notes/astr102/Stellar-Clouds.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">/notes/astr102/Stellar-Clouds.html</guid>
	</item>

	<item>
		<title>Star Formation and Evolution</title>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;Galactic core glows b/c we can&amp;#8217;t see the difference between stars. Disc of the Milky Way Galaxy is ~ 200 pc. Distance to core is 8000 pc. Extra-galactic entities such as the Magellanic Cloud is ~ 60,000 pc away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The galactic core is bulging at the center b/c at least 10% of the stars in the galaxy. Dark lines around the core are gas clouds on line with our view of the core.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Physics 101:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small radius, less rotational inertia, faster rotation&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Large radius, more rotational inertia, slower rotation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id='dark_dust_clouds'&gt;Dark Dust Clouds&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dust clouds preferentially scatters blue light more than red light. Dust clouds occlude most visible light, but one can still see stars through the cloud via infrared b/c it is redder. Similar to the effect of a sunset/ sunrise on the earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dark clouds require neutral, cold atomic hydrogen in the ground state. Temp ~100 K. If all the hydrogen is the ground state, it wouldn&amp;#8217;t be visible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ground state of hydrogen isn&amp;#8217;t exactly a single state/ line. There are two possible ground states. This transition is called a hyper-fine transition or hyper-fine line (for the emission line).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='molecular_clouds'&gt;Molecular Clouds&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clouds that are composed of various molecules such as CO_2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='gas_clouds'&gt;Gas Clouds&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cloud might begin spinning b/c gravity can torque a spinning object, which causes the object torquing the spinning object to gain angular momentum. If a dust cloud spins generally, it falls along the spin axis b/c it is opposed by the force of the spinning cloud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are always a small amount of ionized particles in interstellar space. The gas conducts electricity. Therefore, the cloud interacts with the magnetic field of the interstellar space. The magnetic field of a dust cloud is ~ 1E-6 of the Earth&amp;#8217;s. As the cloud contracts, it compresses the field lines. This exerts pressure on the field lines, creating magnetic tension in the field line. These forces attempt to dissipate the cloud. Dust cloud gas can move along the field lines, causing the cloud to flatten over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cosmic rays (high-energy particles in space) can also interact with the magnetic field, causing an inward pressure on the cloud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gas clouds are an unstable system. Once the field lines go into under-dense areas, it tends to break the cloud up into smaller, denser clouds&lt;/p&gt;</description>
		<pubDate>Thu, 31 Jan 2013 12:32:00 -0500</pubDate>
		<link>/notes/astr102/Star-Formation-and-Evolution.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">/notes/astr102/Star-Formation-and-Evolution.html</guid>
	</item>

	<item>
		<title>Problem Set 2</title>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;a)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;delay = R * T_prop&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;T_prop = distance / prop_speed T_prop = 5 000 000 m / 2.5 * 10^8 m / s T_prop = 0.02 s&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;R = 1.5 * 10^6 b/s&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;delay = 30 000 b&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5 * 10^5 bits A -&amp;gt; B&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;02 s&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;R / t_prop&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5 * 10^6 b/s * 0.02 s = 30 000 b&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;d)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;T_delay = T_prop + T_trans&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;T_trans = size / R T_trans = 45E5 b / 15E6 b/s T_trans ~= 0.3 s&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;T_delay = 0.02 s + 0.3 s = 0.32 s&lt;/p&gt;</description>
		<pubDate>Thu, 31 Jan 2013 12:16:00 -0500</pubDate>
		<link>/notes/comp431/Problem-Set-2.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">/notes/comp431/Problem-Set-2.html</guid>
	</item>

	<item>
		<title>Protocols and Service Layers</title>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;What is a protocol? A set of conventions governing how you format data and how respond and talk to each other. All communication activity on the Internet is governed by protocols. Specific messages are sent and specific actions are taken when messages are received. Protocols define a format and order of messages sent and received and actions taken upon receipt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='protocol_layers'&gt;Protocol Layers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Networks are composed of many &amp;#8216;pieces&amp;#8217;. Solution: decompose functions into a stack of function &amp;#8216;layers&amp;#8217;. Each layer provides &amp;#8216;services&amp;#8217; to the layer above it and uses the services below it. Allows implementation of layers to be separate as long as the interface of the layer remains the same. Each layer can treat everything below it in the stack as a &amp;#8216;black box&amp;#8217;. Each layer talks with its peer layer in a distributed system. Layer headers act like stacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? Explicit structure allows identifying and relating complex system&amp;#8217;s pieces. Modularization eases maintenance. Changing implementation doesn&amp;#8217;t affect other parts of the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could it be harmful? There is additional data added on by each layer. If the black box is mis-implemented, it could result in subtle errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='layer_functions'&gt;Layer Functions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id='error_control'&gt;Error Control&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Error control makes the logical channel between layers reliable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='flow_control'&gt;Flow Control&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avoid overwhelming a peer by sending data&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='segmentation__reassembly'&gt;Segmentation &amp;#38; Reassembly&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Partitioning large message into smaller ones and reassembling them&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='multiplexing'&gt;Multiplexing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interleaving data signals.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
		<pubDate>Thu, 31 Jan 2013 11:55:00 -0500</pubDate>
		<link>/notes/comp431/Protocols-and-Service-Layers.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">/notes/comp431/Protocols-and-Service-Layers.html</guid>
	</item>

	<item>
		<title>Problem Set 1</title>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;A)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;T = 8F + 8h d = T / R total = d * N&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;total = ( (8F + 8h)/R ) * M&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;B)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;packet = 8P + 8h total_size = M * packet total_time = total_size / R&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;total = ( N * ( M * (8P * 8h) ) ) / R&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P = F/M M = F/L&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;total = ( M * (8F * 8h) ) / R&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;C)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;total_time T_a + trans_time trans_time = total_size / R total_size = M * packet packet = 8P + 4h&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;total_time = T_a + trans_time trans_time = total_size / R total_size = 8F + 4h&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When F is much greater than size of P. Whenever there is a lossy connection between A and B. When there is delay between transmissions between A and B. 1 GB &amp;#8211;&amp;gt; A &amp;#8211;&amp;gt; R1&lt;/p&gt;</description>
		<pubDate>Tue, 29 Jan 2013 11:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
		<link>/notes/comp431/Problem-Set-1.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">/notes/comp431/Problem-Set-1.html</guid>
	</item>

	<item>
		<title>Delay</title>
		<description>&lt;h2 id='perhop_delay_nodal_delay'&gt;Per-Hop Delay (&amp;#8220;nodal delay&amp;#8221;)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the delay of the internet? Nobody knows. Some researchers have done research on edge systems and on how universities connect to the internet. Even these sort of networks are massive and variable. No one really knows how much queuing delay occurs overall in the internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;d_nodal = d_proc + d_queue + d_trans + d_prop&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;d_proc = processing delay - typically a few microseconds or less&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;d_queue = queuing delay (La/R) - depends on congestion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;q_trans = transmission delay (L/R) - signficant for low-speed links&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;d_prop = propagation delay - a few microseconds to hundreds of milliseconds (depends on # of nodes)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='internet_traffic_measurements__models'&gt;Internet Traffic Measurements &amp;amp; Models&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What dominates end-to-end delay? It is largely a function of the # of routers encountered along the path from source to destination. Router delay is equivalent to d_nodal&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you measure it? Capture every TCP/IP packet header on the link between two networks, i.e., UNC and the internet. 1 hour trace for 1Gbps is ~= 30+ GB file. Store, sort, process terabytes of data to find the connections that have occured. Good questions: how long is each packet delay? How variable is the delay?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;d_queue dominates d_nodal on the internet. d_prop and d_trans over a given connection rarely change. d_proc can change, but it isn&amp;#8217;t a huge contributer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember that all rates are averages. Even on a 10 millisecond timeframe, instant packet rate can shoot up a large amount.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
		<pubDate>Tue, 29 Jan 2013 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
		<link>/notes/comp431/Delay.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">/notes/comp431/Delay.html</guid>
	</item>

	<item>
		<title>Solar Fusion Reactions</title>
		<description>&lt;h2 id='protonproton_chain_reaction'&gt;Proton-Proton Chain Reaction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fusion reaction combines protons into energy, positrons, Helium-4, and neutrinos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two protons collide a weak-interaction scale producing a deuterium, a positron, and an electron neutrino:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title='proton'&gt;p+&lt;/abbr&gt; + p+ &amp;#8594; &lt;abbr title='deuterium/ deuteron'&gt;H-2&lt;/abbr&gt; + &lt;abbr title='positron'&gt;e+&lt;/abbr&gt; + &lt;abbr title='electron neutrino'&gt;nu-e&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The positron almost immediately runs into an electron and annihilates, producing energy (2 gamma rays):&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title='positron'&gt;e+&lt;/abbr&gt; + &lt;abbr title='electron'&gt;e-&lt;/abbr&gt; &amp;#8594; 2 &lt;abbr title='photon (energy)'&gt;ph&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The electron neutrino, which only interacts with weak-force and gravity, escapes the sun without running into anything&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deuterium and a proton collide producing Helium-3 and a gamma ray (a &lt;abbr title='photon (energy)'&gt;ph&lt;/abbr&gt;oton)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title='deuterium/ deuteron'&gt;H-2&lt;/abbr&gt; + &lt;abbr title='proton'&gt;p+&lt;/abbr&gt; &amp;#8594; H&lt;abbr title='electron'&gt;e-&lt;/abbr&gt;3 + &lt;abbr title='photon (energy)'&gt;ph&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 Helium-3 combines to become helium-4 &amp;amp; 2 protons&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;H&lt;abbr title='electron'&gt;e-&lt;/abbr&gt;3 + &lt;abbr title='helium-3'&gt;He-3&lt;/abbr&gt; &amp;#8594; H&lt;abbr title='electron'&gt;e-&lt;/abbr&gt;4 + 2 &lt;abbr title='proton'&gt;p+&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The overall reaction:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6 &lt;abbr title='proton'&gt;p+&lt;/abbr&gt; &amp;#8594; H&lt;abbr title='electron'&gt;e-&lt;/abbr&gt;4 + 2 &lt;abbr title='proton'&gt;p+&lt;/abbr&gt; + 2 &lt;abbr title='positron'&gt;e+&lt;/abbr&gt; + 2 &lt;abbr title='electron neutrino'&gt;nu-e&lt;/abbr&gt; + 2 &lt;abbr title='photon (energy)'&gt;ph&lt;/abbr&gt;;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id='cno_cycle'&gt;CNO cycle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trace amounts of carbon &amp;amp; nitrogen are not fused in the core, but are used as nuclear catalysts. Used in transition states, but then goes back to its raw form&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='relative_energies'&gt;Relative Energies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proton-proton energy production is greater than CNO energy release in our sun, but increased can overwhelm p-p reactions over 15 million &amp;#176;K&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 P &amp;#8594; Helium-4: mass difference = 0.048 * 10 &lt;sup&gt;-27&lt;/sup&gt; kg&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;600 million tons of hydrogen into ~ 600 million tons per second&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;~ 4.3 million tons of hydrogen goes into energy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id='distant_stars'&gt;Distant Stars&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Properties of stars&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;distance&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;radius&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;temperature&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;mass of star&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;luminosity&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;chemical composition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id='how_do_you_determine_the_distance'&gt;How do you determine the distance?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;AUs&lt;/dt&gt;

&lt;dd&gt;average distance between sun &amp;amp; earth&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearest star: ~100,000 AUs away&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using geometry w/ parallax - Move a given distance, measure the angle between the two spots&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parallax in astronomy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;measurement 1: Earth in July&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;measurement 2: Earth in Jan&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;equals distance of 2 AUs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The closer the start, the larger the shift relative to the background&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For small angles: tan &amp;#952; ~~ &amp;#952;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Must use radians for this approximation to work&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;for radians: - tan p = (1 AU / p) or for small p, p ~= (1 AU / d)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;for seconds of arc: - d = (206,265 AU / p)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;d = r / p is a new unit: a parsec (AUs per arc second)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 parsec ~~ 3.3 light years&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Jan 2013 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
		<link>/notes/astr102/solar-fusion-reactions.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">/notes/astr102/solar-fusion-reactions.html</guid>
	</item>

	<item>
		<title>Network Switching</title>
		<description>&lt;h2 id='message_switching'&gt;Message Switching&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How fast can you transmit a 7.5Mb message over a network w/ 1.5 Mbps links&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each hop: you must read entire message, checksum message and then read headers and send to next switch&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;3 hops = 15 second transmission time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interactive experiences are delayed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lossy network leads to very long delays&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;T = ((dataSize / bandwidth) * timeBetweenHops * hops)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id='packet_switching_store_and_forward'&gt;Packet Switching (Store and Forward)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How fast?&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5 Mb = 5,000 packets of 1,500 bits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Each packet travels to between switches in ~2 ms&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Each router can send packets faster, b/c it doesn&amp;#8217;t have to read an entire file&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;T = (packets * (packetSize / bandwidth)) * (timeBetweenHops * hops)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;3 hops = 4 ms, so 5,000 packets = 5 s&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;~ 3 times faster than message switching on average&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;However: packets must hold sequence numbers to ensure correct ordering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id='forwarding'&gt;Forwarding&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The process of moving packets among routes from a source to a destination&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;There are various approaches&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Datagram networks must look up address each forward&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Virtual circuits determine hops only once&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Delayed expense vs. Long call setup&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id='datagram_network'&gt;Datagram Network:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each packet carries a destination address&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Destination address used to look up next hop&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Route (next hop) may change at any time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id='how_it_works'&gt;How it works&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Packets contain a complete destination address: a network &amp;amp; host&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Router examines destination address&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Forwards packet to next closest router&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Router maintains a table of &amp;#8220;next hop&amp;#8221; to all destination networks&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Router maintains no per-connection state&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id='virtual_circuit_path_network'&gt;Virtual circuit (path) network:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;packets carry a &amp;#8216;tag&amp;#8217; (virtual circuit ID) that determines next hop&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;path determined at call setup time &amp;amp; lives throughout call&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Routers maintain per-call path state&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id='how_it_works'&gt;How it works&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A static route is computed &amp;amp; assigned an ID (VC #)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Router maintains per-connection state &amp;amp; must perform setup/ tear-down&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Packets contain VC id (different per router). Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Router can only know that the VC isn&amp;#8217;t used only if it&amp;#8217;s per router&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Otherwise: there would be a large amounts of collisions due to routers choosing the same VC&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Much simpler problem to solve on a per-router basis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id='network_structure'&gt;Network Structure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Taxonomy of networks - Telecommunication networks: - Circuit Switched: - FDM - TDM - Packet-switched: - Networks w/ VC - Datagrams&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id='network_core'&gt;Network Core&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Routers&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Network of networks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id='network_edge'&gt;Network Edge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;End systems (hosts)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;live at edge&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;run applications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interaction paradigms: - Client/ server model: - Client requests, receives service from server - WWW browser/ server email client/ server - Peer-to-peer model: - Host interactions symmetric - File sharing (Napster, BitTorrent, etc)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id='access_networks'&gt;Access Networks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Physical media: communication links&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to connection end-systems to edge router?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Residential access networks&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Institutional/ enterprise access networks&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Mobile access networks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Issues:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;transmission speed?&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;shared vs. dedicated?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id='transport_services'&gt;Transport Services&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 main types: connection-oriented and connectionless&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Applications using TCP - HTTP, FTP, Telnet, SMTP&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Applications using UDP - DNS, streaming media, teleconferencing, internet telephony&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id='connectionoriented_service'&gt;Connection-oriented service&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goal: transfer data between end systems&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Handshaking: setup data transfer ahead of time&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;#8220;Hello, hello back&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Set up &amp;#8220;state&amp;#8221; in two communicating hosts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transmit data&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Connection-oriented services on the internet: TCP (RFC 793)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id='tcp_service_model'&gt;TCP Service Model&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Defined in the context of a &amp;#8216;connection&amp;#8217;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;reliable, in-order, byte-stream - losses detected and recovered from&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;flow control: sending won&amp;#8217;t overwhelm receiver&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;congestion control: senders &amp;#8216;slow down sending rate&amp;#8217; when network is congested&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id='connectionless_services'&gt;Connection-less services&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goal: transfer data between end systems&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advantage: if the application doesn&amp;#8217;t not need reliability or you do not want to wait, use connection-less services&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the wild: UDP (RFC 768)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;unreliable data transfer&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;no flow control&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;no congestion control&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Jan 2013 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
		<link>/notes/comp431/Switching.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">/notes/comp431/Switching.html</guid>
	</item>

	<item>
		<title>Sun Composition</title>
		<description>&lt;h2 id='corona'&gt;Corona&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Very high temp: ~ 1 million&amp;#176;K&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Completely different from other layers of the sun&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Low density, white color&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;How diffuse is it? - 1 liter of water over a sphere the size of the earth&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Temperature is high, but not much heat (too diffuse)&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Emits high energy radiation (way above visible light)&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Size &amp;amp; energy of corona varies by solar activity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id='heat_vs_temp'&gt;Heat vs. Temp&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Temp: avg. kinetic energy (in a gas, actual motion) - high temp = fast moving particles&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Heat: energy transferred by collisions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id='why_is_it_hot'&gt;Why is it hot?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We don&amp;#8217;t quite know, we have some ideas: - Both prominences &amp;amp; flares heat the corona&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Transitions from 6000&amp;#176;K to 1 million&amp;#176;K&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id='solar_magnetic_fields'&gt;Solar magnetic fields&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2 million tons of matter per second&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trivial compared to total mass of the sun&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Only about 0.1% has boiled off&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some field lines extend into space, some loop back around&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a large scale the solar wind looks constant, but it varies over time&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;22 year cycle of the sun&amp;#8217;s field lines flipping&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sunspot cycles occur over the rising and failing of this cycle (i.e., twice per cycle)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id='sun_spots'&gt;Sun spots&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All told cooler than the surface of the sun&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Umbra is the darkest &amp;amp; coolest (~4500&amp;#176;K) spot of sunspot&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Penumbra is the lighter &amp;amp; hotter (~4800&amp;#176;K) gray part&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Caused by magnetic fields&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Material flows between an outward-facing sunspot to an inward-facing sunspot&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Emits Synchrotron emission, sunspots are very radio loud&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Sunspots happen in pairs&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Sunspots occur between 40&amp;amp;deg N; and 40&amp;#176; S&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Minimum occurs at 40&amp;#176; N/S&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Maximum occurs at 20&amp;#176; N,S&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id='why_do_they_happen'&gt;Why do they happen?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When look at the spectrum of a sunspot, they have 2 more emission lines than the rest of the sun&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relates to quantum physics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;spin-up vs spin-down&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;W/o magnetic field, electrons keep their spin&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;W/ a magnetic field, electrons can change their spin&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;This results in 2 ground states &amp;amp; 2 excited states (4 possible emissions), but spin-up &amp;amp; spin-down are the same energy. Thus, there are multiple absorption lines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The magnetic field of the sun at the sun spot is entirely perpendicular to the sun &amp;#8211; It either comes straight out of the sun or straight into the sun&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The magnetic field affects the charged particles in the sun&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Magnetic field suppresses convection, so the sun spot cools down - Particles spiral around magnetic field lines&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sun is mainly composed of a gas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Doesn&amp;#8217;t rotate as a perfect body, rotates differentially&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Equator rotates faster than poles&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Drags on the magnetic lines, causing kinks&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Eventually they break from the main lines &amp;amp; create sunspots&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id='sunspot_history'&gt;Sunspot History&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discovered around 1600-1700 AD. This was during a period known as the Maudner minimum, a period of reduced solar activity&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We know there are prolonged periods of minimal activity, but no prolonged periods of maximum activity&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id='prominences'&gt;Prominences&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Material traveling along magnetic field lines that will fall back down to surface of the sun&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Hotter than the surface of the sun&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id='solar_flares'&gt;Solar Flares&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These particles are flung off with such force that they overcome the magnetic field of the sun&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Material that makes up the solar win&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Even hotter than prominences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id='coronal_mass_ejections'&gt;Coronal Mass Ejections&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Somewhat like a flare, but magnetically contained&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Magnetic fields twist such that a bubble of charged gas is ejected from the sun&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Happens ~ once a week to several a day depending on solar activity&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Magnetic field of CME can join with the magnetic field of the Earth&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Charged particles follow magnetic lines down to the atmosphere of the Earth, creating radiation as they impact the particles in the atmosphere&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Jan 2013 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
		<link>/notes/astr102/sun-composition.html</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">/notes/astr102/sun-composition.html</guid>
	</item>


	</channel>
</rss>
